Guide to the Peter Davison Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Peter Davison papers
1938-2005
YCAL MSS 727
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
15.21
(16 boxes)
The Peter Davison Papers provide evidence of the career and personal life of author and editor Peter Davison. In addition to documenting Davison's professional and literary circles, the papers also provide insight into Davison's creative output, including his books of poetry (such as The Breaking of the Day and Other Poems and Walking the Boundaries: Poems, 1957-1974 ) and his autobiography ( Half Remembered: A Personal History ). The papers are comprised of business and personal correspondence, writings, 1 audio compact disk, photographs, personal papers, and other papers by or relating to Peter Davison.
Davison, Peter, 1928-2004
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Peter Davison, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 16 (CD): Restricted Fragile Material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Peter Davison (1928-2004)
Davison was a poet and literary editor for the Atlantic Monthly Press and Atlantic Monthly. He was born on June 27, 1928 in New York City to Edward and Natalie Weiner Davison. He began his editorial career at Harcourt, Brace in New York after graduating from Harvard University in 1949. In 1956 Davison joined the Atlantic Monthly Press where he worked in several capacities, including executive editor, director, and senior editor, until 1985. From 1985 to 1998 Davison was the poetry editor for Houghton Mifflin.
Davison maintained a writing career in tandem with his career as a literary editor. He published several books of poetry in addition to his autobiography Half Remembered: A Personal History (1973). His books of poetry include: The Breaking of the Day and Other Poems (1964), Walking the Boundaries: Poems, 1957-1974 (1974), and Breathing Room: New Poems (2000). Davison also edited One of the Dangerous Trades: Essays on the Work and Workings of Poetry (1991) and The Fading Smile: Poets in Boston, 1955-1960, from Robert Frost to Robert Lowell to Sylvia Plath (1994).
Davison married Jane Auchincloss Truslow, a writer, on March 7, 1959. They had two children: Edward Angus and Lesley Truslow. Following his first wife's death in 1981, Davison married the architect Joan Edelman Goody on August 11, 1984.
Davison died of pancreatic cancer on December 29, 2004 in Boston, Massachusetts.
Scope and Contents
The Peter Davison Papers provide evidence of the career and personal life of author and editor Peter Davison. In addition to documenting Davison's professional and literary circles, the papers also provide insight into Davison's creative output, including his books of poetry (such as The Breaking of the Day and Other Poems and Walking the Boundaries: Poems, 1957-1974 ) and his autobiography ( Half Remembered: A Personal History ). The papers are comprised of business and personal correspondence, writings, 1 audio compact disk, photographs, personal papers, and other papers by or relating to Peter Davison.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence, 1941-2002. Series II. Personal and Family Papers, 1938-1950s. Series III. Professional Papers, 1954-1995. Series IV. Writings, 1957-2003. Series V. Other Papers, 1970s-2005.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Editors -- United States; Publishers and publishing -- United States; Born digital; Electronic documents; Photographs; Coles, Robert, 1929-; Davison, Peter, 1928-2004; Ford, Jesse Hill, 1928-1996; O'Connor, Edwin; Swenson, May, 1913-1989; Atlantic Monthly Press
- Correspondence, 1941-2002, undated; Series I; 7; (7 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into two subseries: Business Correspondence and Personal Correspondence.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains Peter Davison's business and personal correspondence. Business correspondence is primarily comprised of Davison's editorial correspondence for the Atlantic Monthly Press. Family correspondence can also be found in Series II. Additional business correspondence, including Davison's work as a jury member for the Pulitzer Prize, is in Series III. Correspondence relating to specific writing projects is located in Series IV.
  - Business Correspondence
    - Alvarez, Beth, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Blount, Ray, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Bowen, Catherine Drinker, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - Coles, Robert, 1956-1983; 9 (Box 1)
    - Coles, Robert, 1956-1983 (Box 1)
    - Davison, Peter (Box 1)
    - Fitzgerald, Frances, 1968, 1981; 2 (Box 1)
    - Ford, Jesse Hill, 1970-1983; 5 (Box 1)
    - Guillen, Jorge, 1965-1972 (Box 1)
    - Heat Moon, William Least, 1981-1983; 2 (Box 1)
    - Herge, 1982-1983; 2 (Box 1)
    - Ingatow, David, 1982-1983; 2 (Box 1)
    - Jones, Rodney, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Kennan, George F., 1960-1969 (Box 1)
    - Matthews, William, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Moynihan, Daniel Patrick, 1978-1983; 4 (Box 1)
    - Mossman, James, 1960s-1971; 2 (Box 2)
    - O'Connor, Edwin, 1948-1981; 8 (Box 2)
    - Porter, Katherine, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Powers, J. F. [empty folder], 1970 (Box 2)
    - Priestley, J. B., 1965-1972; 3 (Box 2)
    - Randall, Clarence, 1960s (Box 2)
    - Reid, Alastair, 1970s-1980s (Box 2)
    - Russell, Bertrand, 1966, 1970-1972 (Box 2)
    - Seferis, George, 1968-1973; 2 (Box 2)
    - Starbuck, George, 1982-1984 (Box 2)
    - Swenson, May, 3 (Box 2)
    - Ustinov, Peter, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Warner, William, 1982-1984; 3 (Box 2)
    - Weeks, Edward, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Wills, Garry, 1982-1983; 2 (Box 2)
    - Zuckerman, Mortimer, 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - Various business correspondence, 2 (Box 2)
  - Personal Correspondence
    - Arranged Chronologically
      - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1942-1943 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1944-1945 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1945-1949 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1951-1953 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1955-1958 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1955-1959 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1958-1960 (Box 3)
      - Various correspondents, 1959-1961 (Box 3)
      - Letters: Teddie and Rose, 1960s (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 1981; 2 (Box 4)
      - Japan Trip, 1982 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 1983; 2 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 1984; 2 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 1985; 2 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 1986; 2 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 1987; 2 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 1988; 3 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 1989; 2 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 1990; 3 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 1991; 2 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 1992; 2 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 1994; 2 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 1995; 4 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 1992-2000; 2 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 1992-2000; 9 (Box 6)
      - Correspondence, 1992-2000; 7 (Box 6)
      - Correspondence, 2000-; 2 (Box 6)
    - Arranged Alphabetically by Correspondent
      - Allanbrook, Douglas (Box 7)
      - Brelis, Dean, 1950-1955 (Box 7)
      - Davidson, Edward (Box 7)
      - Davidson, Edward - posthumous (Box 7)
      - Davidson, Lesley and Harriet Barry, 1952 (Box 7)
      - Ford, Harry, 1966-1986; 5 (Box 7)
      - Harvard University Press (Box 7)
      - Herzog, Fred, 1960s (Box 7)
      - Hite, G - Roman Letters, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
      - Jerome, Judson, business correspondence (Box 7)
      - Jones, Howard M (Box 7)
      - Kazin, Alfred (Box 7)
      - Lindley, Frances (Box 7)
      - Matthews, William, business correspondence (Box 7)
      - Mayne, Richard (Box 7)
      - Merwin, William S., 2 (Box 7)
      - Mowat, Claire (Box 7)
      - Perrin, Forrest (Box 7)
      - Plath, Sylvia (Box 7)
      - Pitts, Dudley (Box 7)
      - Priestley, J. B., 1970s (Box 7)
      - Reid, Alastair (Box 7)
      - Schaffer, Peter, 1950-1975 (Box 7)
      - Updike, John (Box 7)
      - Warren, Robert Penn (Box 7)
- Personal and Family Papers, 1938-1950s, undated; Series II; 1; (1 box)
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  Series II contains personal and family papers, including correspondence, early writing projects, journals, and school papers.
  - Family History Materials (Box 8)
  - Lazarus Herzog correspondence (Box 8)
  - Granny Weiner - personal correspondence (Box 8)
  - Madeline Kaliz (Hexter) (Box 8)
  - L. Blenkinsop correspondence (Box 8)
  - Various school papers - Boulder, 1940s (Box 8)
  - Various school papers (Box 8)
  - Journal, 1938 (Box 8)
  - Various writings - "Juvenilia" (Box 8)
  - Writing, 1947 (Box 8)
  - Writings - St. John's College, 1949-1950 (Box 8)
  - "Senate page" papers and "Hearsay" prospectus (Box 8)
  - Drama, Harvard University (Box 8)
  - Personal file, Before 1949 (Box 8)
  - Personal file, 1949-1950 (Box 8)
  - Army file, 2 (Box 8)
  - "Black Book", 1949-1950; 2 (Box 8)
  - Book reviews and jackets, 1950s (Box 8)
  - Various (Box 8)
- Professional Papers, 1954-1995, undated; Series III; 1; (1 box)
  Series III contains professional papers in addition to some personal papers. Included is printed material about Davison and correspondence relating to Davison's work as a jury member for the Pulitzer Prize.
  - Employment - Harvard, California, R.I. School, 1954-1962 (Box 9)
  - Music reviews, 1959-[?] (Box 9)
  - Villa Serbelloni, correspondence, 1970s (Box 9)
  - Rome, 1971 (Box 9)
  - Articles, 1972 (Box 9)
  - Rome, 1972; 2 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence regarding writings, 1984-1986 (Box 9)
  - Pulitzer Prize Correspondence, 1984 (Box 9)
  - Articles about Peter Davison, 1980s (Box 9)
  - "The Boston TAB", 1992 February 18 (Box 9)
  - "National Geographic", 1994 January (Box 9)
  - Writings on James Merrill, 1995 (Box 9)
  - Printed material (Box 9)
  - Various papers (Box 9)
  - Historical Documents (Box 9)
  - Robert Frost House, business correspondence (Box 9)
  - Memorabilia, 2 (Box 9)
  - "Half Remembered" reviews, etc. (Box 9)
  - Various files (Box 9)
- Writings, 1957-2003, undated; Series IV; 5; (5 boxes)
  Series IV is organized into three subseries: Poetry and Nonfiction; Readings, Speeches, and Robert Frost Materials; and Reviews, Correspondence, and Publishing Papers.
  Series IV is comprised of drafts, proofs, and galleys relating to Davison's publications. The series also includes drafts and research relating to Davison's public appearances (such as readings and speeches). Correspondence relating to writing projects can be found in this series.
  - Poetry and Nonfiction
    - Breaking of the Day - setting copy, 1964 (Box 10)
    - Breaking of the Day - page proofs, 1963 October 7 (Box 10)
    - Breaking of the Day - galleys, 1963 August 28 (Box 10)
    - The City and the Island - setting copy, 1966 (Box 10)
    - The City and the Island - page proofs, 1966 (Box 10)
    - Pretending To Be Asleep - setting copy, 1970 (Box 10)
    - Pretending To Be Asleep - first proof, 1969 October 9 (Box 10)
    - Pretending To Be Asleep - second proof, 1969 October 28 (Box 10)
    - Half Remembered - setting typescript, 1973 February 7; 2 (Box 10)
    - Walking the Boundaries - setting typescript, undated (Box 10)
    - The Dance of Hours - misc., 1973, 1977 (Box 10)
    - The Dance of Hours - setting typescript, 1984; 2 (Box 10)
    - Praying Wrong - page proofs, 1984 Sept 5; 2 (Box 10)
    - Barn Fever - notes, 1980 (Box 10)
    - Barn Fever - typescript, corrected, undated (Box 10)
    - Barn Fever - setting copy, undated (Box 10)
    - Barn Fever - page proofs, 1980 (Box 10)
    - The Great Ledge - typescript, 1988 (Box 10)
    - The Great Ledge - typescript, 1989 (Box 10)
    - The Great Ledge - setting typescript, 1989 (Box 10)
    - The Great Ledge - author's proofs, 1989 (Box 10)
    - The Great Ledge - printer's proofs, first, 1989 (Box 10)
    - The Great Ledge - printer's proofs, third, 1989 (Box 10)
    - The Great Ledge - Designer's Mock Up, 1989 (Box 10)
    - Voice in the Mountain - typescript, corrected by Robert Penn Warren, 1977 (Box 11)
    - Voice in the Mountain - typescript, corrected, undated (Box 11)
    - Voice in the Mountain - proofs, corrected, 1977 (Box 11)
    - Walking the Boundaries, manuscript (Box 11)
    - Walking the Boundaries - duplicate proof, English, 1973 (Box 11)
    - Discarded Poems, 1949-1986 (Box 11)
    - "Cyclialbian", 1950 (Box 11)
    - "The Sea Horse", 1957 (Box 11)
    - Unpublished Articles, 1960s (Box 11)
    - "The Unfailed Writer" (Box 11)
    - Occasional Verse (Box 11)
    - Poems, 1995-2000 (Box 11)
    - Unpublished writings? (Box 11)
    - Atlantic articles on poetry (Box 11)
    - Atlantic articles [by Peter Davison] (Box 11)
    - Travel piece on Olympus - never finished (Box 11)
    - American Heritage Articles (Box 11)
    - Lowell-Dickey article [empty] (Box 11)
    - Papers Relating to "Fading Smiles"
      - Lists for "Fading Smiles" (Box 12)
      - Booth Material (Box 12)
      - Davison Material (Box 12)
      - Donald Hall Material (Box 12)
      - Holmes Material (Box 12)
      - Hardwick Material (Box 12)
      - Kumin Material (Box 12)
      - Kunitz Material, 2 (Box 12)
      - Lowell Material (Box 12)
      - MacLeish Material (Box 12)
      - Merwin Material (Box 12)
      - Sylvia Plath Material, 2 (Box 12)
      - Poets Theatre (Box 12)
      - Adrienne Rich Material (Box 12)
      - Anne Sexton Material (Box 12)
      - Sissman Material, 2 (Box 12)
      - Starbuck Material (Box 12)
      - Sweeney Material (Box 12)
      - Wilbur Material (Box 12)
      - Photographs, 2 (Box 12)
      - Negatives (Box 12)
      - Photographs, 2 (Box 12)
      - Fading Smile, page proofs for (Box 12)
  - Readings, Speeches, and Robert Frost Materials
    - Speeches on publishing (Box 13)
    - Readings and introductions, 1963-1983 (Box 13)
    - Readings, 1983-1991 (Box 13)
    - Readings, 1992-2003 (Box 13)
    - "Natural Enemies", 1971 (Box 13)
    - "The Real Voices of Modern Poetry" (Box 13)
    - "Madness in Modern Poetry" (Box 13)
    - "The Family" (Box 13)
    - "The City and the Island" (Box 13)
    - "Pity, Peace and Love" (Box 13)
    - "Apocalypse," Wheaton Graduation, 1969 (Box 13)
    - Speeches at Smith College, Harvard University (Box 13)
    - Reading Schedule, 2000 (Box 13)
    - Thomas Hardy Reading (Box 13)
    - "Jupiter: What Poetry Does for Language" (Box 13)
    - "What Poetry Does to Language", 2 (Box 13)
    - Emerson College Lectures (Box 13)
    - Baylor Lecture (Box 13)
    - "Versions and Veils" (Box 13)
    - "The Poet as Editor" (Box 13)
    - New England Monthly, Robert Frost essay (Box 13)
    - Atlantic Monthly, Robert Frost essay (Box 13)
    - Robert Frost Centennial Documentation (Box 13)
    - Robert Frost Centennial Clippings (Box 13)
    - Papers regarding Robert Frost (Box 13)
    - Robert Frost lecture, 1998; 2 (Box 13)
    - Robert Frost speeches (Box 13)
  - Reviews, Correspondence, and Publishing Papers
    - Reviews: General (Box 14)
    - "The Breaking of the Day" - comments (Box 14)
    - "The City and the Island" - reviews and comments (Box 14)
    - "Dark Houses," correspondence, etc (Box 14)
    - Reviews: "Barn Fever" and "Voice on Mountain" (Box 14)
    - "Barn Fever" - Atheneum correspondence and reviews (Box 14)
    - "The Great Ledge" - reviews, etc. (Box 14)
    - "Praying Wrong" - reviews, 3 (Box 14)
    - "Walking the Boundaries" [Reviews, etc.], 2 (Box 14)
    - "Walking the Boundaries" - copyrights (Box 14)
    - "A Voice in the Mountain" [Reviews, etc.] (Box 14)
    - "A Voice in the Mountain" - Atheneum correspondence (Box 14)
    - "Half Remembered" - Heinemann Publishers [correspondence, etc] (Box 14)
    - "Half Remembered" - letters (Box 14)
    - "Half Remembered" [revised edition correspondence, etc] (Box 14)
    - "Pretending To Be Asleep" - comments (Box 14)
    - "Fading Smile" - reviews, etc. (Box 14)
    - "Fading Smile" - permissions (Box 14)
    - "My Say" - correspondence, permissions etc. (Box 14)
    - "The Poems of Peter Davison" - text and proofs (Box 14)
    - Harper and Row [correspondence, etc] (Box 14)
    - Russell and Volkening [correspondence etc.] (Box 14)
    - University of Michigan Press (Box 14)
    - Watershed Foundation Tape (Box 14)
    - Permissions for Publications (Box 14)
- Other Papers, 1970s-2005, undated; Series V; 1; (1 box)
  Series V contains business papers, personal papers, financial records, printed material, and other materials.
  - Peter Davison Biographical Info, 1970s (Box 15)
  - Peter Davison Bio, 2000 (Box 15)
  - Bio, 2002 (Box 15)
  - Fellowships and Grants (Box 15)
  - Programs from Author Events (Box 15)
  - The White House, 1980 (Box 15)
  - Events (Box 15)
  - Book and Author Dinners - Richmond, VA (Box 15)
  - Clippings by and about Peter Davison (Box 15)
  - Atlantic Monthly - History (Box 15)
  - Publishing History (Box 15)
  - Knopf correspondence, etc. (Box 15)
  - Knopf contracts (Box 15)
  - Knopf royalties (Box 15)
  - Knopf/Norton royalties (Box 15)
  - Knopf/Random House royalties (Box 15)
  - Yaddo (Box 15)
  - Transcripts of Interviews with Peter Davison (Box 15)
  - Peter Davison Memorials, 2004-2005 (Box 15)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Computer disk is restricted. Copies of electronic files may be requested through Access Services
    2007-YCAL-7164-0001: Remembering Peter Davison, June 25, 2005
  - "Alfred," Interview typescript (Box 15)
  - Photocopies of Doris Holmes papers (Box 15)
  - Various papers (Box 15)
  - Harvard 50th Reunion (Box 15)
  - Edward Davison POWs (Box 15)
  - Masefield, John - autograph letter, signed, to Edward Davison, undated (Box 15)
  - Peter Davison letter to Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, 1977 (Box 15)
  - Photograph of Mark Twain, undated (Box 15)
- Computer media, 0.21; (1 box)
  - Remembering Peter Davison June 25, 2005, 2007-ycal-7164-0001; 1 (Box 16)
    Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.